<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>william-dawson.github.io - Personal Blog</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/feeds/personal-blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://william-dawson.github.io/</id><updated>2024-02-10T11:00:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Predicting potential SARS-CoV-2 mutations of concern via full quantum mechanical modelling</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/predicting-potential-sars-cov-2-mutations-of-concern-via-full-quantum-mechanical-modelling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-10T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2024-02-10T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2024-02-10:/predicting-potential-sars-cov-2-mutations-of-concern-via-full-quantum-mechanical-modelling.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I share a paper I worked on about predicting virus mutations with Density Functional Theory.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have another paper to share, this time called &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2023.0614"&gt;Predicting potential SARS-CoV-2 mutations of concern via full quantum mechanical modelling&lt;/a&gt;. In this paper, we used our BigDFT code to model the binding of SARS-CoV-2's spike protein to the human ACE2 receptor. Based on this analysis, we proposed a mutation (A484K) that might appear in the Omicron strain in the future. Our experimentalist colleagues then validated this prediction (don't worry, they didn't make any real viruses). In fact, this mutation did end up appearing in BA.2.86 while we were going through the peer review process. These results give us confidence that such predictions can be done with a BigDFT workflow going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, we held a &lt;a href="https://molsc.riken.jp/mpqcp2024_ws_en.html"&gt;workshop on quantum chemistry&lt;/a&gt; at the RIKEN main campus in Wako. I was in charge of making the website, so you might notice some design similarities. As I mention in the about section, I made this blog using the &lt;a href="https://github.com/petrnohejl/MinimalXY"&gt;MinimalXY&lt;/a&gt; theme for Pelican. This time I wanted to try a new theme, in particular one based on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Material_Design"&gt;material design&lt;/a&gt;. But I haven't written CSS or HTML by hand since I was a college student! Fortunately, ChatGPT came to the rescue here, and basically was able to generate the whole thing based on my directions. I was incredibly impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the conference was right after the New Year's holiday, I decided to head up early and explore the area. This time I went to Chiba city. It's a pretty fun city; I visited Chiba Port Tower, Inohana Castle, and the Natural History Museum. On the second day, I hopped on a train that went down the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C5%8Ds%C5%8D_Peninsula"&gt;Boso Peninsula&lt;/a&gt;. I was hoping to get nice views of the ocean from the train window. I got that and more: it was a clear enough day that I could see distant Mount Fuji the whole time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Mt. Fuji" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/IMG_0370.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Five Japanese Foods</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/five-japanese-foods.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-10T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-09-10T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2023-09-10:/five-japanese-foods.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a break from the usual research, here are some good things I recommend to eat in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been struggling to figure out what kind of code or chemistry could accompany a post like this. But I think I'll just play it straight and share some recommendations for things to eat in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bokkake Soba&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Bokkake" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the Bokkake Soba that is sold at 神戸灘八 here in Kobe. My 
understanding is that in the Nagata ward of Kobe, there is a famous local food
called "sujikon", which is a mixture of beef tendon and "konnyaku". At 神戸灘八,
they make a kind of noodle dish, which comes with sujikon, egg yolk, etc. It 
has a similar profile to ramen, but it really has a unique flavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Akadashi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sushi restaurants often serve a red miso soup which has fish trimmings in it.
It's really good, the soup has a deep and heavy flavor. If you're like me,
you might walk away from a restarant thinking that was the best part of the
meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Akadashi" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Horumon Udon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparantely I really like noodle dishes from Hyogo prefecture. In this case,
the choice of meat is "Horumon", which I think translates as "offal" (i.e.
various organ parts from the animal, specially cows in this region). The
sauce is more on the sweet side. The main place to get it is the town of Sayo,
which is about an hour from Kobe by train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Horumon Udon" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG4.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Oyaki&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oyaki is another difficult one to find, being limited to the Nagano region.
It is a kind of dumpling made from buckwheat, and it comes with a variety
of fillings ranging form sweet to savory. If you like chinese style dumpings,
I think you will love Oyaki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Oyaki" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG5.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nakau Breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Nakau" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one feels silly, but I promise you will enjoy it. Many of the fast food
restaurants here serve an affordable, rice-based breakfast. Nakau distinguishes
itself by having the best over easy eggs (目玉焼き) and bacon. Granted, it's
not American style bacon, and in my experience I can make a better version at
home, but at least go and get a sense of it. Nakau also has the best miso soup
of the chain restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Honorable Mention: Shio Saba&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm surprised I had to leave this as an honorable mention, as it was really
the first thing I loved after arriving. In my childhood experience, fish was
always served without any skin. This style, by contrast, has the skin on,
which leads to a very fatty taste. When combined with a lot of salt and lemon,
it's great. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Shio Sab" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/jfood/IMG6.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="Japan"></category></entry><entry><title>Protein–ligand interactions from a quantum fragmentation perspective: The case of the SARS-CoV-2 main protease interacting with α-ketoamide inhibitors</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/protein-ligand-interactions-from-a-quantum-fragmentation-perspective-the-case-of-the-sars-cov-2-main-protease-interacting-with-a-ketoamide-inhibitors.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-21T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2023-06-21:/protein-ligand-interactions-from-a-quantum-fragmentation-perspective-the-case-of-the-sars-cov-2-main-protease-interacting-with-a-ketoamide-inhibitors.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I announce a publication about applying our complexity reduction framework to the study of α-ketoamide inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2. I also do some travel blogging about Tromsø, Norway.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to share a new publication &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0148064"&gt;"Protein–ligand Interactions from a Quantum Fragmentation Perspective: The Case of the SARS-CoV-2 Main Protease Interacting with α-Ketoamide Inhibitors"&lt;/a&gt;. This paper combines two cutting edge techniques: linear-scaling Density Functional Theory and polarizable forcefields. We spend a lot of time trying to understand how coherent of a picture they provide. Finally, we use them together to get some insight into the design of new medicines for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an unrelated note, I spent the first week of June in Tromsø, Norway for &lt;a href="https://mrchemsoft.no/nmqc-2023/"&gt;Numerical Methods in Quantum Chemistry 2023&lt;/a&gt;. This was a really nice workshop, with plenty of great talks and lots of deep discussions. Perhaps the highlight was a lengthy keynote by Edward Valeev or to hear about the recent interests of Gregory Beylkin. There were tutorials as well, &lt;a href="https://github.com/BigDFT-group/bigdft-school/tree/main/nmqc-2023"&gt;including one we ran on BigDFT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Photo of Tromsø" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/IMG_9893.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was quite exciting to visit Tromsø. It is located so far north that we could enjoy the midnight sun, at least on the few days it wasn't raining! I didn't know much about Norway before going, only what I remembered from visiting Disneyworld as a kid. Somehow it to delivered on the polar bears, fjords, trolls, boats, and bakeries. Everywhere you can hear seagulls, which awoke some kind of childhood memory. The only thing missing was a stave church, which I can leave as motivation to hopefully visit the rest of Norway someday. No blog post about Norweigian style coffee this time, though I can say I drank some excellent stuff there, especially at a cafe called Tøllefsenhjørnet in town.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading Roundup - April 2023</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/reading-roundup-april-2023.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-17T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-17T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2023-04-17:/reading-roundup-april-2023.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some papers and blog posts I recommend.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Myths and Legends in High-Performance Computing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The director of my institute and some of my colleagues have written a very interesting paper surveying the future of HPC. They break down a number of topics such as accelerators, quantum computing, cloud computing, etc. A couple of their opinions on things like memory bandwidth are particularly worth paying attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02432"&gt;Available on Arxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linear-scaling implementation of molecular electronic self-consistent field theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I'm getting interested in the minimization approach for O(N) DFT. This paper is based on the exponential paramterization of the density matrix $D(X) = exp[-P(X)S]Dexp[SP(X)]$, where the exponential is used to keep the density matrix idempotent. One of the nice features of this paper is that they consider simultaneously minimization for a fixed Hamiltonian and for the self-consistent Hamiltonian. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/full/10.1063/1.2464111"&gt;Available in JCP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Generating accurate density matrices on the tangent space of a Grassmann manifold&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note, starting from a given good density matrix, how do you predict a better one for a new potential or set of atomic coordinates, given the constraints (idempotency, trace)? This is a topic that been addressed recently using the (at least obscure to me) framework of Grassmann mainfolds. This recent work by Tan and Lao show that you can even use this extrapolation technique for constructing potential energy surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/full/10.1063/5.0137775"&gt;Available in JCP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mistakes in Fortran 90 Programs That Might Surprise You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is as advertised, I definitely made several of these mistakes when first getting used to Fortran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cs.rpi.edu/~szymansk/OOF90/bugs.html"&gt;Available Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="recommendations"></category></entry><entry><title>French Coffee</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/french-coffee.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-01T12:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-04-01T12:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2023-04-01:/french-coffee.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my recent trip to France, I have some thoughts and experiments about how to brew a "un café".&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last few weeks, I have been in France attending various meetings. Thanks to my work, I have been lucky enough to visit several times over the years. One thing that has left an impression on me is the coffee, whether it's enjoyed standing at the bar or lounging on the terrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French typically drink espresso, but it is different from what you would get in Italy or the United States. In fact, on various occasions, I have been asked if I would prefer the coffee French or Italian style. The French drink is long, filling the cup to the top, whereas the Italian drink (often called a ristretto) is short and sweet. I wanted to know the details of these differences so that I could recreate the experience at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WD: What is the usual ratio of coffee in to drink out in a ristretto?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT: A ristretto is a type of espresso shot that is made by using the same amount of coffee as a regular espresso, but with half the amount of water. The usual ratio for a ristretto is about 1:1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I have heard that the ratio for espresso is typically 1:1 or 1:1.5. In Europe, the espresso baskets are usually 14.5 grams for a double shot, but a single shot, which is more commonly consumed, would be around 7-10 grams. On the other hand, in the United States, we prefer our extra large baskets, so it's normal to get a 30-gram double espresso drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WD: What is the usual ratio of coffee in to drink out in French espresso?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT: I'm sorry, but I'm not familiar with a type of espresso called "French espresso."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't worry ChatGPT, you're not alone. I've scoured the English-speaking internet and found no solid descriptions. Maybe my blog will be incorporated in a future GPT version, because I intend to answer this question here. To do so, I took the step of ordering espresso served in paper cups at two different cafes, and brought the used cups back to Japan. I committed to memory the amount of coffee in those cups, added water to the invisioned line, and weighed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex"&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image1.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image2.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some online sources I found suggested that a French espresso must be a 'lungo' or a 1:3 ratio, but that's not even close. We need to go up to a 1:7 ratio, which means 50 grams of drink out with just 7 grams of coffee in. This is similar to the trendy 'Turbo Shot' or Scott Rao's 'allongé'. I decided to tighten the recipe up a bit and see if I could pull 2 espressos using 15 grams of coffee in and 90 grams out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex"&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image3.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image4.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going coarser took a lot of trial and error, but when the I saw the coffee violently flowing out, I was instantly transported back to those Paris cafes. My final attempt came out in 40 seconds, which is probably too slow, but I was happy with what I got. One of the reasons Turbo Shots are popular is that they are forgiving when brewing with coarser grounds, and I think that came through in my shot. It was a lighter drink with no bitterness and a lot of fruity flavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex"&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image5.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image6.jpeg" width="80%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have to say, I was quite happy to enjoy the drink at home during cherry blossom season. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display:flex"&gt;
  &lt;div style="flex:1"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/fcoffee/image7.jpeg" width="90%"/&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Experimental–theoretical study of laccase as a detoxifier of aflatoxins</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/experimental-theoretical-study-of-laccase-as-a-detoxifier-of-aflatoxins.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-23T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2023-01-23:/experimental-theoretical-study-of-laccase-as-a-detoxifier-of-aflatoxins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I share a publication I worked on where we studied the Laccase enzyme for bioremediation application.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I'd like to share a recently published work I did with Marco Zaccaria and Babak Momeni of Boston College (among others). The title is &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-27519-1"&gt;Experimental–theoretical study of laccase as a detoxifier of aflatoxins&lt;/a&gt;. In this paper, we are interested in developing enzymes which can degrade aflatoxins. Aflatoxin contamination is a major concern for food safety; they can contaminate important crops like maize, and are carcinogenic if ingested. There is great interest in finding ways to break down these toxins, such as using engineered enzymes. Laccase has potential for this task, but has several limitations. In this work, we used both experimental and computational techniques to assess one particular Laccase's ability to break down two toxins: AFB1 and AFG2. The interesting result is that even though they have a very similar structure, the degradation dynamics are dramatically different. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Density functional theory calculations of large systems: Interplay between fragments, observables, and computational complexity</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/density-functional-theory-calculations-of-large-systems-interplay-between-fragments-observables-and-computational-complexity.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-10T17:39:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-10-10T17:39:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-10-10:/density-functional-theory-calculations-of-large-systems-interplay-between-fragments-observables-and-computational-complexity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I announce a new publication which explores the potential of linear scaling DFT for practical calculations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce a new publication available in WIREs Computational 
Molecular Science entitled
&lt;a href="https://wires.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/wcms.1574"&gt;Density functional theory calculations of large systems: Interplay between fragments, observables, and computational complexity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years now, it has been possible to use our &lt;a href="https://bigdft.org/"&gt;BigDFT&lt;/a&gt; 
code to perform DFT calculations on systems composed of many thousands of 
atoms. As someone who is primarily interested in the computational side of
things, this felt like a clear win. Nonetheless, for a code to be really useful
it has to prove its worth in actual studies. For this review, we wanted to look
at what kind of real DFT studies are being performed on large systems in hopes
that we would gain insight for future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, there are fewer application papers than one would expect given
the capabilities of existing DFT codes. One challenge is that larger systems 
are more complex, so it is even harder to go from a single point calculation to 
actual rational insight. Therefore calculations on large systems must be 
conceived quite differently than when working on small, model systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address this issues, we defined a framework of study based on the concept
of a "quasiobservable". In a standard quantum mechanical investigation, we 
treat the full system as one coherent unit, and compute observables of the
entire system. At a large scale, however, it becomes possible to break down
a system into a set of well defined fragments, which are mutually entangled.
Then, we can define quasiobservables which are associated with each fragment 
(or sets of fragments). These quasiobservables become localized descriptors
of a system which can be more easily turned into insight about emergent
properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the way we described our framework is new, we found many excellent
studies which are already using such an approach. I hope that our review can
highlight these new types of studies and that it will inspire you towards 
new research projects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Discovery of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro peptide inhibitors from modelling substrate and ligand binding</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/discovery-of-sars-cov-2-mpro-peptide-inhibitors-from-modelling-substrate-and-ligand-binding.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-09T17:38:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T17:38:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-10-09:/discovery-of-sars-cov-2-mpro-peptide-inhibitors-from-modelling-substrate-and-ligand-binding.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I announce a new publication involving the development of new COVID-19 medicines.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce a new publication available in Chemical Science entitled
&lt;a href="https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2021/sc/d1sc03628a"&gt;Discovery of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro peptide inhibitors from modelling substrate and ligand binding&lt;/a&gt;.
This was a collaborative effort involving many people. Our study involved both
experimental and theoretical work (docking, classical molecular dynamics, QM/MM, 
linear-scaling DFT, etc). My contribution, of course, was on the linear-scaling
DFT side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main protease of SARS-CoV-2 (Mpro) plays a central role in replication
of the virus. Mpro works as a kind of scissors that cuts up large polypeptides
in specific places. If one can design a drug that binds strongly to the
protease without being degraded, the protease can be deactivated, which 
would prevent  the virus from replicating. In this paper, we studied the 
binding mechanism of the protease in order to rationally design potential 
drugs. We examined both how it binds to the cleavage sites of the polypeptides
and a large database of small molecule inhibitors. This analysis gave us
design rules that helped us design new peptides which effectively inhibit
the protease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am curious what the reader experience will be like with this paper. I imagine 
that some readers will focus in on their particular expertise, and find 
themselves wishing we presented more calculations. For a multi-disciplinary 
paper like this though, I think quantity is its own kind of quality. You have
to find the signal that is coming through from the sum total of your analysis
techniques. This isn't to say each step wasn't caried out thoroughly, but just
a reminder that each technique is merely a tool which helps you get to that
final step of designing and experimentally testing the new drug. The paper is
available as open access so I hope you give it a read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Some Mid-Pandemic Thoughts on Running</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/some-mid-pandemic-thoughts-on-running.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-17T17:38:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T17:38:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-04-17:/some-mid-pandemic-thoughts-on-running.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A year into the COVID-19 pandemic, I describe my new hobby of running, and why it is so much fun in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since about May of last year, I've taken up running as a hobby. Usually I try
to stay active by playing basketball or futsal with people from work, but
pandemic restrictions have put an end to that. It's been about a year since
I started, and I really am enjoying it, so I wanted to write a blog post
about why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all comes back to that famous middle school formula: $$\pi r^2$$. When you
first start running, you get out of the house, do a loop around the
neighborhood, and come back panting. You get a little bit of that runner's
high, but mainly it just feels like work. But as the months go by, you start
to be able to run longer and longer distances. That's when you realize that
it's not the distance that matters, but the area of the circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without giving away too much personal information, I live in the city of
Nishinomiya now, which has at its center Nishinomiya station. On google maps,
I can hover above that station, and search "points of interest".
From Nishinomiya station there is Nishinomiya Shrine about half a kilometer
away, so the beginner can enjoy taking a loop around a beautiful shrine.
About one kilometer away is Shukugawa park, a park with a nice long river
and a long line of cherry blossom trees. As you start to get your legs you
can take a visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d13114.252404064842!2d135.33859122100577!3d34.74140551934538!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x6000f2429396d4e7%3A0x80d4db7e4d62994b!2sNishinomiya%20Station!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sjp!4v1618650138672!5m2!1sen!2sjp" width="400" height="350" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five kilometers is about the shortest distance you can run without feeling like
a total failure. Turning south from Shukugawa park, you can make it to 
Omaehama park, which has a small beach and a nice view of the ocean. Round
trip from the station should be just the right distance. If you go north,
you'll find yourself turning around at Hirota shrine, which is a wide and
open shrine with a great view as you approach. If you go east and run along
the train line, you will arrive at Koshien station, where you can see Japan's
most famous baseball stadium and its iconic ivy. The round trip is about 5.5
kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months of running, I discovered that my wallet wasn't in my pocket.
I had to double back the entire route to look for it, and that's how I ran
my first 10K of the season (the wallet was at home the entire time). From Nishinomiya
station, if you're willing to gain some elevation, in under 10K you can make
it all the way up to Kabutoyama Forest Park (and the nearby Kwansei Gakuin
University) which has a spectacular view of the city. If you go south west,
there is a small (artificial?) island which has a free footbath you can use,
which makes for a great stopping point. Of course that's not the right attitude
if you care about how fast you're running, but that's missing the point. The
real fun of running in Japan is all the places you can discover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="png" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/assets/IMG_7596.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan has one of the best train systems in the entire world. So if you really
want to expand you range, taking the train home will instantly double the
distance you can travel. If you run east, you can make it to Amagasaki Castle,
and you know you made a good decision about a hobby when an ancient castle
is the destination. Running to Takarazuka city along the Muko river was also
a great experience. If you go west until Ashiya and then go north along the
river, you can find my favorite hiking course. At the entrace, there is a
small waterfall (look for Taki no Chaya on the map) which is right before
the paved roads end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most I have done in this pandemic stretch is just over 20K. I've already
had to leave out a lot of great destinations, and with the radius now expanded
to 20K it almost becomes an impossible task. Recently I find myself stuck
looking at google maps instead of sleeping because I want to plan long distance
runs. Due to the pandemic, I try to wear a mask whenever there are other
people anywhere nearby, which means there are a few destinations I haven't yet
made it to because I know the streets are going to be crowded the whole way. 
But I'm optimistic about the coming year, and hope to report on some future
adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>BigDFT Tutorials</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/bigdft-tutorials.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-01T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-02-01:/bigdft-tutorials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I present a new set of tutorials for the BigDFT software.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, we have been creating a new version of the website for the BigDFT
code. One of the goals for the new website is to present a new workflow
for using BigDFT. In the past, the code was used by preparing input files
manually and then running the program. However, for a few years now we
have been developing the PyBigDFT python bindings for BigDFT [1]. The new
workflow will have you write python code that can handle everything from 
pre-processing, to running calculations, to analyzing the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we have been developing some new tutorials for how to
use the code. Each of these tutorials is build from a jupyter notebook that
we imported into sphinx. I think this is a very fun way to write tutorials,
you can almost do a mini study and share it with the world. Every time I
add to the tutorials, I realize there are some new features I would like to
develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to try to demonstrate in these tutorials is the ability
of PyBigDFT to work with other code bases. To me, being able to quickly mix
a variety of libraries is the exceptional part of python. In my recent
tutorial on 
&lt;a href="https://l_sim.gitlab.io/bigdft-suite/lessons/GeometryOptimization.html"&gt;Geometry Optimization&lt;/a&gt;,
I do just this. In the first part, we go
from a SMILES string to an optimized geometry, by integrating 
&lt;a href="http://openbabel.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;openbabel&lt;/a&gt; into
a BigDFT workflow. In the second part, a slab is created with the aid of
the &lt;a href="https://wiki.fysik.dtu.dk/ase/"&gt;Atomic Simulation Environment&lt;/a&gt;. In 
&lt;a href="https://l_sim.gitlab.io/bigdft-suite/lessons/MachineLearning.html"&gt;another tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
, I integrate PyBigDFT with a machine learning framework called
&lt;a href="https://www.qmlcode.org/index.html"&gt;qmlcode&lt;/a&gt;. Developing clear datastructures
that enable transformations like this is definitely one of our goals for
PyBigDFT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Ratcliff, Laura E., William Dawson, Giuseppe Fisicaro, Damien Caliste,
Stephan Mohr, Augustin Degomme, Brice Videau et al. "Flexibilities of wavelets
as a computational basis set for large-scale electronic structure
calculations." The Journal of Chemical Physics 152, no. 19 (2020): 194110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>BigDFT Webinar</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/bigdft-webinar.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-23T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2020-10-23:/bigdft-webinar.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On November twelfth, we will be hosting a webinar about the BigDFT code entitled The Flexibilities of Wavelets for Electronic Structure  Calculations in Large Systems.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On November twelfth, we will be hosting a webinar about the BigDFT
code entitled &lt;a href="http://www.max-centre.eu/webinar/flexibilities-wavelets-electronic-structure-calculations-large-systems"&gt;The Flexibilities of Wavelets for Electronic Structure 
Calculations in Large Systems&lt;/a&gt;. If
you are interested in electronic structure software or its applications
to large systems (1000+ atoms) I think you will find it quite interesting.
We will be presenting material that should be interesting to both
chemists and people who do materials science. The webinar is free to
attend, so feel free to join!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="workshop"></category></entry><entry><title>My Article in The Sankei News</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/my-article-in-the-sankei-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-01T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2020-09-01:/my-article-in-the-sankei-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An article I wrote for The Sankei News called "The Appeal of Chemistry You Can Do At Home" has been published.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce that an article I wrote has appeared in
&lt;a href="https://www.sankei.com/west/news/200829/wst2008290003-n1.html"&gt;The Sankei News&lt;/a&gt;.
The title of the article is "The Appeal of Chemistry You Can Do At Home".
The article is written in Japanese. I received a lot of help from people at
RIKEN and the editor at the newspaper to turn my poor Japanese into what
appears to be a coherent article. The article also features an illustration
created by my talented wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't offer a translation here, but I would like to summarize the main
points. In this article, I discuss how I, like many researchers at RIKEN,
have been working from home as a measure to prevent the spread of COVID-19.
Of course, upon hearing that many people will wonder "how can you research
chemistry at home?" To answer this, I give an overview of what simulation
is and how we can do it from the comfort of home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the article, I tried to discuss something more personal to me.
One of the things I enjoy about doing science is those "aha!" moments. In
that sense, I think computational chemistry is really ideal. It's a constant
bombardment of little successes. Each simulation you run gives you more
information about what you're studying. And each line of code you write is 
gives you deeper insight into the theory that you are modelling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the most enjoyable science is the science with the quickest time from
question to answer. The trick to quick turnaround time is to build good tools
that can be re-used to study new problems. This is not so easy when you
are an experimentalist, you can't build a robot to replace you, and you rarely
have the opportunity to design new equipment. But in simulation science, we
very easily can extend the toolsets we have. This is a privilege we developers
should keep in mind and use as motivation to build the most powerful and
easy to use tools we can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>CPMD 2017 Workshop</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/cpmd-2017-workshop.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-27T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-10-27T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2017-10-27:/cpmd-2017-workshop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I describe my experience at the CPMD2017 workshop in Tsukuba Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was able to attend the
&lt;a href="http://www.nims.go.jp/MII-I/CPMD2017/"&gt;CPMD2017 workshop&lt;/a&gt; in Tsukuba, Japan.
CPMD in this case stands for Car-Parrinello molecular dynamics, one of the
most important techniques in computational physics. This workshop featured
talks from some of the top scientists in the field, including of course both
Roberto Car and Michele Parrinello.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop also coincided with the 70th birthday of Dr. Roberto Car. It was
fun to see people celebrate as he certainly had a big impact on the scientific
careers of many people there. On a less positive note, this workshop all
coincided with Typhoon Lan. I hope that everyone from the conference was able
to safely and smoothly return home despite the severe weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is CPMD and what it is useful for? First principles techniques such as
density functional theory can be used to compute the ground state energy of
a given molecular system. This works well for computing things like bulk
crystal systems, but what about dynamically evolving systems such as liquid
water? In that case, we need to be able to compute the motion of atoms as well.
This combination of molecular dynamics and density functional theory is an
important tool for interpreting experiment, and studying systems under extreme
conditions. Car and Parrinello were pioneers in combining molecular dynamics
with density functional theory, including inventing the method now called
Car-Parrinello molecular dynamics which was first introduced in their 1985
paper [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, the most impactful talk was given by Dr. Osamu Sugino from
the University of Tokyo. In his talk, he referenced his group's work on
using first-principles molecular dynamics simulations to study firefly
bioluminescence [2]. For this study, it was necessary for them to relax the
structure of the oxyluciferin anions in solution. This simulation proved to
be very slow to converge, but in a true tour de force calculation they spent
200 days performing this simulation using 128 Xeon processors for each isomer.
These time consuming simulations are an inspiration to us who work on the
computational side, reminding us how important it is to get the best performance
out of our codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Car, Richard, and Mark Parrinello. "Unified approach for molecular
dynamics and density-functional theory." Physical review letters 55,
no. 22 (1985): 2471.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Noguchi, Yoshifumi, Miyabi Hiyama, Motoyuki Shiga, Osamu Sugino, and
Hidefumi Akiyama. "Reverse Stability of Oxyluciferin Isomers in Aqueous
Solutions." The Journal of Physical Chemistry B 120, no. 34 (2016): 8776-8783.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="workshop"></category></entry></feed>