<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>william-dawson.github.io - Personal Blog</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/feeds/personal-blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/</id><updated>2021-10-10T17:39:38+09:00</updated><entry><title>Density functional theory calculations of large systems: Interplay between fragments, observables, and computational complexity</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/density-functional-theory-calculations-of-large-systems-interplay-between-fragments-observables-and-computational-complexity.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-10T17:39:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-10-10T17:39:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-10-10:/Test-Website/density-functional-theory-calculations-of-large-systems-interplay-between-fragments-observables-and-computational-complexity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I announce a new publication which explores the potential of linear scaling DFT for practical calculations.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce a new publication available in WIREs Computational 
Molecular Science entitled
&lt;a href="https://wires.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/wcms.1574"&gt;Density functional theory calculations of large systems: Interplay between fragments, observables, and computational complexity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years now, it has been possible to use our &lt;a href="https://bigdft.org/"&gt;BigDFT&lt;/a&gt; 
code to perform DFT calculations on systems composed of many thousands of 
atoms. As someone who is primarily interested in the computational side of
things, this felt like a clear win. Nonetheless, for a code to be really useful
it has to prove its worth in actual studies. For this review, we wanted to look
at what kind of real DFT studies are being performed on large systems in hopes
that we would gain insight for future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, there are fewer application papers than one would expect given
the capabilities of existing DFT codes. One challenge is that larger systems 
are more complex, so it is even harder to go from a single point calculation to 
actual rational insight. Therefore calculations on large systems must be 
conceived quite differently than when working on small, model systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address this issues, we defined a framework of study based on the concept
of a "quasiobservable". In a standard quantum mechanical investigation, we 
treat the full system as one coherent unit, and compute observables of the
entire system. At a large scale, however, it becomes possible to break down
a system into a set of well defined fragments, which are mutually entangled.
Then, we can define quasiobservables which are associated with each fragment 
(or sets of fragments). These quasiobservables become localized descriptors
of a system which can be more easily turned into insight about emergent
properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the way we described our framework is new, we found many excellent
studies which are already using such an approach. I hope that our review can
highlight these new types of studies and that it will inspire you towards 
new research projects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Discovery of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro peptide inhibitors from modelling substrate and ligand binding</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/discovery-of-sars-cov-2-mpro-peptide-inhibitors-from-modelling-substrate-and-ligand-binding.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-09T17:38:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-10-09T17:38:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-10-09:/Test-Website/discovery-of-sars-cov-2-mpro-peptide-inhibitors-from-modelling-substrate-and-ligand-binding.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I announce a new publication involving the development of new COVID-19 medicines.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce a new publication available in Chemical Science entitled
&lt;a href="https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2021/sc/d1sc03628a"&gt;Discovery of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro peptide inhibitors from modelling substrate and ligand binding&lt;/a&gt;.
This was a collaborative effort involving many people. Our study involved both
experimental and theoretical work (docking, classical molecular dynamics, QM/MM, 
linear-scaling DFT, etc). My contribution, of course, was on the linear-scaling
DFT side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main protease of SARS-CoV-2 (Mpro) plays a central role in replication
of the virus. Mpro works as a kind of scissors that cuts up large polypeptides
in specific places. If one can design a drug that binds strongly to the
protease without being degraded, the protease can be deactivated, which 
would prevent  the virus from replicating. In this paper, we studied the 
binding mechanism of the protease in order to rationally design potential 
drugs. We examined both how it binds to the cleavage sites of the polypeptides
and a large database of small molecule inhibitors. This analysis gave us
design rules that helped us design new peptides which effectively inhibit
the protease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am curious what the reader experience will be like with this paper. I imagine 
that some readers will focus in on their particular expertise, and find 
themselves wishing we presented more calculations. For a multi-disciplinary 
paper like this though, I think quantity is its own kind of quality. You have
to find the signal that is coming through from the sum total of your analysis
techniques. This isn't to say each step wasn't caried out thoroughly, but just
a reminder that each technique is merely a tool which helps you get to that
final step of designing and experimentally testing the new drug. The paper is
available as open access so I hope you give it a read.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="publication"></category></entry><entry><title>Some Mid-Pandemic Thoughts on Running</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/some-mid-pandemic-thoughts-on-running.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-17T17:38:38+09:00</published><updated>2021-04-17T17:38:38+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-04-17:/Test-Website/some-mid-pandemic-thoughts-on-running.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A year into the COVID-19 pandemic, I describe my new hobby of running, and why it is so much fun in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since about May of last year, I've taken up running as a hobby. Usually I try
to stay active by playing basketball or futsal with people from work, but
pandemic restrictions have put an end to that. It's been about a year since
I started, and I really am enjoying it, so I wanted to write a blog post
about why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all comes back to that famous middle school formula: $$\pi r^2$$. When you
first start running, you get out of the house, do a loop around the
neighborhood, and come back panting. You get a little bit of that runner's
high, but mainly it just feels like work. But as the months go by, you start
to be able to run longer and longer distances. That's when you realize that
it's not the distance that matters, but the area of the circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without giving away too much personal information, I live in the city of
Nishinomiya now, which has at its center Nishinomiya station. On google maps,
I can hover above that station, and search "points of interest".
From Nishinomiya station there is Nishinomiya Shrine about half a kilometer
away, so the beginner can enjoy taking a loop around a beautiful shrine.
About one kilometer away is Shukugawa park, a park with a nice long river
and a long line of cherry blossom trees. As you start to get your legs you
can take a visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d13114.252404064842!2d135.33859122100577!3d34.74140551934538!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x6000f2429396d4e7%3A0x80d4db7e4d62994b!2sNishinomiya%20Station!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sjp!4v1618650138672!5m2!1sen!2sjp" width="400" height="350" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five kilometers is about the shortest distance you can run without feeling like
a total failure. Turning south from Shukugawa park, you can make it to 
Omaehama park, which has a small beach and a nice view of the ocean. Round
trip from the station should be just the right distance. If you go north,
you'll find yourself turning around at Hirota shrine, which is a wide and
open shrine with a great view as you approach. If you go east and run along
the train line, you will arrive at Koshien station, where you can see Japan's
most famous baseball stadium and its iconic ivy. The round trip is about 5.5
kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months of running, I discovered that my wallet wasn't in my pocket.
I had to double back the entire route to look for it, and that's how I ran
my first 10K of the season (the wallet was at home the entire time). From Nishinomiya
station, if you're willing to gain some elevation, in under 10K you can make
it all the way up to Kabutoyama Forest Park (and the nearby Kwansei Gakuin
University) which has a spectacular view of the city. If you go south west,
there is a small (artificial?) island which has a free footbath you can use,
which makes for a great stopping point. Of course that's not the right attitude
if you care about how fast you're running, but that's missing the point. The
real fun of running in Japan is all the places you can discover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="png" src="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/assets/IMG_7596.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan has one of the best train systems in the entire world. So if you really
want to expand you range, taking the train home will instantly double the
distance you can travel. If you run east, you can make it to Amagasaki Castle,
and you know you made a good decision about a hobby when an ancient castle
is the destination. Running to Takarazuka city along the Muko river was also
a great experience. If you go west until Ashiya and then go north along the
river, you can find my favorite hiking course. At the entrace, there is a
small waterfall (look for Taki no Chaya on the map) which is right before
the paved roads end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most I have done in this pandemic stretch is just over 20K. I've already
had to leave out a lot of great destinations, and with the radius now expanded
to 20K it almost becomes an impossible task. Recently I find myself stuck
looking at google maps instead of sleeping because I want to plan long distance
runs. Due to the pandemic, I try to wear a mask whenever there are other
people anywhere nearby, which means there are a few destinations I haven't yet
made it to because I know the streets are going to be crowded the whole way. 
But I'm optimistic about the coming year, and hope to report on some future
adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>BigDFT Tutorials</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/bigdft-tutorials.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-01T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2021-02-01:/Test-Website/bigdft-tutorials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I present a new set of tutorials for the BigDFT software.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, we have been creating a new version of the website for the BigDFT
code. One of the goals for the new website is to present a new workflow
for using BigDFT. In the past, the code was used by preparing input files
manually and then running the program. However, for a few years now we
have been developing the PyBigDFT python bindings for BigDFT [1]. The new
workflow will have you write python code that can handle everything from 
pre-processing, to running calculations, to analyzing the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we have been developing some new tutorials for how to
use the code. Each of these tutorials is build from a jupyter notebook that
we imported into sphinx. I think this is a very fun way to write tutorials,
you can almost do a mini study and share it with the world. Every time I
add to the tutorials, I realize there are some new features I would like to
develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to try to demonstrate in these tutorials is the ability
of PyBigDFT to work with other code bases. To me, being able to quickly mix
a variety of libraries is the exceptional part of python. In my recent
tutorial on 
&lt;a href="https://l_sim.gitlab.io/bigdft-suite/lessons/GeometryOptimization.html"&gt;Geometry Optimization&lt;/a&gt;,
I do just this. In the first part, we go
from a SMILES string to an optimized geometry, by integrating 
&lt;a href="http://openbabel.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;openbabel&lt;/a&gt; into
a BigDFT workflow. In the second part, a slab is created with the aid of
the &lt;a href="https://wiki.fysik.dtu.dk/ase/"&gt;Atomic Simulation Environment&lt;/a&gt;. In 
&lt;a href="https://l_sim.gitlab.io/bigdft-suite/lessons/MachineLearning.html"&gt;another tutorial&lt;/a&gt;
, I integrate PyBigDFT with a machine learning framework called
&lt;a href="https://www.qmlcode.org/index.html"&gt;qmlcode&lt;/a&gt;. Developing clear datastructures
that enable transformations like this is definitely one of our goals for
PyBigDFT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Ratcliff, Laura E., William Dawson, Giuseppe Fisicaro, Damien Caliste,
Stephan Mohr, Augustin Degomme, Brice Videau et al. "Flexibilities of wavelets
as a computational basis set for large-scale electronic structure
calculations." The Journal of Chemical Physics 152, no. 19 (2020): 194110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="software"></category></entry><entry><title>BigDFT Webinar</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/bigdft-webinar.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-23T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-10-23T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2020-10-23:/Test-Website/bigdft-webinar.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On November twelfth, we will be hosting a webinar about the BigDFT code entitled The Flexibilities of Wavelets for Electronic Structure  Calculations in Large Systems.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On November twelfth, we will be hosting a webinar about the BigDFT
code entitled &lt;a href="http://www.max-centre.eu/webinar/flexibilities-wavelets-electronic-structure-calculations-large-systems"&gt;The Flexibilities of Wavelets for Electronic Structure 
Calculations in Large Systems&lt;/a&gt;. If
you are interested in electronic structure software or its applications
to large systems (1000+ atoms) I think you will find it quite interesting.
We will be presenting material that should be interesting to both
chemists and people who do materials science. The webinar is free to
attend, so feel free to join!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="workshop"></category></entry><entry><title>My Article in The Sankei News</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/my-article-in-the-sankei-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-01T01:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T01:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2020-09-01:/Test-Website/my-article-in-the-sankei-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An article I wrote for The Sankei News called "The Appeal of Chemistry You Can Do At Home" has been published.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am happy to announce that an article I wrote has appeared in
&lt;a href="https://www.sankei.com/west/news/200829/wst2008290003-n1.html"&gt;The Sankei News&lt;/a&gt;.
The title of the article is "The Appeal of Chemistry You Can Do At Home".
The article is written in Japanese. I received a lot of help from people at
RIKEN and the editor at the newspaper to turn my poor Japanese into what
appears to be a coherent article. The article also features an illustration
created by my talented wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't offer a translation here, but I would like to summarize the main
points. In this article, I discuss how I, like many researchers at RIKEN,
have been working from home as a measure to prevent the spread of COVID-19.
Of course, upon hearing that many people will wonder "how can you research
chemistry at home?" To answer this, I give an overview of what simulation
is and how we can do it from the comfort of home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the article, I tried to discuss something more personal to me.
One of the things I enjoy about doing science is those "aha!" moments. In
that sense, I think computational chemistry is really ideal. It's a constant
bombardment of little successes. Each simulation you run gives you more
information about what you're studying. And each line of code you write is 
gives you deeper insight into the theory that you are modelling. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the most enjoyable science is the science with the quickest time from
question to answer. The trick to quick turnaround time is to build good tools
that can be re-used to study new problems. This is not so easy when you
are an experimentalist, you can't build a robot to replace you, and you rarely
have the opportunity to design new equipment. But in simulation science, we
very easily can extend the toolsets we have. This is a privilege we developers
should keep in mind and use as motivation to build the most powerful and
easy to use tools we can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>CPMD 2017 Workshop</title><link href="https://william-dawson.github.io/Test-Website/cpmd-2017-workshop.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-27T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2017-10-27T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>William Dawson</name></author><id>tag:william-dawson.github.io,2017-10-27:/Test-Website/cpmd-2017-workshop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I describe my experience at the CPMD2017 workshop in Tsukuba Japan.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was able to attend the
&lt;a href="http://www.nims.go.jp/MII-I/CPMD2017/"&gt;CPMD2017 workshop&lt;/a&gt; in Tsukuba, Japan.
CPMD in this case stands for Car-Parrinello molecular dynamics, one of the
most important techniques in computational physics. This workshop featured
talks from some of the top scientists in the field, including of course both
Roberto Car and Michele Parrinello.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This workshop also coincided with the 70th birthday of Dr. Roberto Car. It was
fun to see people celebrate as he certainly had a big impact on the scientific
careers of many people there. On a less positive note, this workshop all
coincided with Typhoon Lan. I hope that everyone from the conference was able
to safely and smoothly return home despite the severe weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is CPMD and what it is useful for? First principles techniques such as
density functional theory can be used to compute the ground state energy of
a given molecular system. This works well for computing things like bulk
crystal systems, but what about dynamically evolving systems such as liquid
water? In that case, we need to be able to compute the motion of atoms as well.
This combination of molecular dynamics and density functional theory is an
important tool for interpreting experiment, and studying systems under extreme
conditions. Car and Parrinello were pioneers in combining molecular dynamics
with density functional theory, including inventing the method now called
Car-Parrinello molecular dynamics which was first introduced in their 1985
paper [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, the most impactful talk was given by Dr. Osamu Sugino from
the University of Tokyo. In his talk, he referenced his group's work on
using first-principles molecular dynamics simulations to study firefly
bioluminescence [2]. For this study, it was necessary for them to relax the
structure of the oxyluciferin anions in solution. This simulation proved to
be very slow to converge, but in a true tour de force calculation they spent
200 days performing this simulation using 128 Xeon processors for each isomer.
These time consuming simulations are an inspiration to us who work on the
computational side, reminding us how important it is to get the best performance
out of our codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Car, Richard, and Mark Parrinello. "Unified approach for molecular
dynamics and density-functional theory." Physical review letters 55,
no. 22 (1985): 2471.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Noguchi, Yoshifumi, Miyabi Hiyama, Motoyuki Shiga, Osamu Sugino, and
Hidefumi Akiyama. "Reverse Stability of Oxyluciferin Isomers in Aqueous
Solutions." The Journal of Physical Chemistry B 120, no. 34 (2016): 8776-8783.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Personal Blog"></category><category term="workshop"></category></entry></feed>